A Guide to the Penny C. Morrill Collection, circa 1970-1980
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Penny C. Morrill Collection circa 1970-1980
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
104
4 boxes (1.67 linear feet)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Penny Morrill, 1986-1997.
Biographical/Historical Information
Penny Morrill is a local historian and author. In the 1970s she wrote four books about the architecture of historic Alexandria. In 1979 she was the curator for Who Built Alexandria? Architects in Alexandria, 1750-1900, an exhibition at Carlyle House that documented the building trades in Old Town Alexandria. Ms. Morrill served as president of the Historic Alexandria Foundation. Additionally, in the 1990s she published several books about 20th century Mexican silversmiths.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of correspondence, notes, working papers, copies of primary and secondary source materials, clippings, photographs, and minutes relating to Ms. Morrill's research concerning 18th and 19th century architecture in Alexandria.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series, one with subseries, as follows:
Series 1: Background Materials
Series 2: Who Built Alexandria? Subseries: Background Materials, Alexandria Builders, Alexandria Buildings, General Subjects. Series is organized topically and chronologically, according to the organizational scheme created by Ms. Morrill.
Series 3: Historic Alexandria Foundation
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Historic Alexandria Foundation Collection, Boxes 70A-70F.
Separated Material
Four positive prints from Series 2 have been transferred to the Morrill Collection of the photographs collections.
Index Terms
Architects and Builders - Virginia; Architecture - Virginia - Alexandria
Contents List
- Background Materials, 1732-1981 (Box-folder 104: 1-28)
  Includes records inventories, fire company information, reference images, articles, and notes.
  - Inventories of records, 1981. (Box-folder 104:1)
  - Inventory of records - Arlington County, October 1980. (Box-folder 104:2)
  - Inventory of records - Arlington County, October 1980. (Box-folder 104:3)
  - Fire - General Information - Fire Department and other interesting facts, 1732-1889. (Box-folder 104:4)
  - Fire - Alexandria Fire Department History/Alexandria Hose and Engine Company, 1811-1868. (Box-folder 104:5)
  - Fire - Sun Fire Company, 1800-1888. (Box-folder 104:6)
  - Fire - History of Friendship Fire Company, 1800-1863. (Box-folder 104:7)
  - Fire - History of Friendship Fire Company, 1864-1899. (Box-folder 104:8)
  - Fire - History of Hydraulion Steam Fire Engine Company, 1827-1903. (Box-folder 104:9)
  - Fire - Sanborn maps of Alexandria, 1877-1931. (Box-folder 104:10)
  - Pictures - Police, Masonic Lodge. (Box-folder 104:11)
  - Pictures - Miscellaneous, 1913-1959. (Box-folder 104:12)
  - Pictures - Alexandria City Hall, Market House, Market Square, 1860-1950. (Box-folder 104:13)
  - Secondary Sources - published articles, 1869-1880. (Box-folder 104:14)
  - Secondary Sources - published articles, 1961-1977. (Box-folder 104:15)
  - Secondary Articles, no dates. (Box-folder 104:16)
  - Secondary Sources - unpublished, Alexandria Plans and Precedents, 1978. (Box-folder 104:17)
  - Secondary Sources - unpublished, Market Square, introduction, 1977. (Box-folder 104:18)
  - Notes - Legal, 1800-1933. (Box-folder 104:19)
  - Notes - The Charter and Laws of the City of Alexandria, 1878(?). (Box-folder 104:20)
  - Notes - Miscellaneous. (Box-folder 104:21)
  - Notes - Minutes of Meetings, 1752-1853. (Box-folder 104:22)
  - Notes - Arts books, 1813-1853. (Box-folder 104:23)
  - Notes - Alexandria Gazette,1785-1870. (Box-folder 104:24)
  - Notes - Alexandria Gazette,1871-1891. (Box-folder 104:25)
  - Notes - Annual financial statements, City of Alexandria, 1822-1922. (Box-folder 104:26)
  - Early History of the Alexandria Market Square by Penny Morrill, December 22, 1981; History and Description of City Hall, Alexandria, Virginia, historical accounty by Penny Morrill, September 9, 1981. (Box-folder 104:27)
  - Alexandria City Hall Renovation, Exhibit Design Sources, November 6, 1981. (Box-folder 104:28)
- Who Built Alexandria? (Box 104-104B)
  Information on individual architects and builders, as well as selected buildings. Also contains a subject folder (Box 104B, Folder 45) on black construction.
  - Background Materials (Box-folder 104:29-33)
    - National Register of Historic Places Inventory - Nomination Form - Alexandria City Hall and Market House, December 1981. (Box-folder 104:29)
    - Information on America's City Halls, May 29, 1981. (Box-folder 104:30)
    - Historic Structures Report: Alexandria City Hall, January 18, 1982. (Box-folder 104:31)
    - Alexandria City Hall Preservation Recommendations, November 2, 1981. (Box-folder 104:32)
    - Specifications (First Draft): Alterations and Additions to East and West Wings City Hall Building, Alexandria, Virginia. (Box-folder 104:33)
  - Alexandria Builders (Box 104A)
    - James McGuire (Box-folder 104A:1)
    - William Lovering (Box-folder 104A:2)
    - Benjamin Latrobe (Box-folder 104A:3)
    - Alexander Lyles (Box-folder 104A:4)
    - John Lambdin (Box-folder 104A:5)
    - Going Lamphier (Box-folder 104A:6)
    - Emmanuel Francis (Box-folder 104A:7)
    - Richard Conway (Box-folder 104A:8)
    - Adolph Cluss (Box-folder 104A:9)
    - Philip Dwyer (Box-folder 104A:10)
    - John Carlyle (Box-folder 104A:11)
    - Glenn Brown (Box-folder 104A:12)
    - John Bogue (Box-folder 104A:13)
    - William McKnight (Box-folder 104A:14)
    - George L. Seaton (Box-folder 104A:15)
    - Robert Mills (Box-folder 104A:16)
    - Thomas Tefft (Box-folder 104A:17)
    - James Wren (Box-folder 104A:18)
    - John Wise (Box-folder 104A:19)
    - William F. Vincent (Box-folder 104A:20)
    - William Yeaton (Box-folder 104A:21)
    - Ammi Young (Box-folder 104A:22)
    - B.F. Price (Box-folder 104A:23)
    - B.F. Price, Other Buildings. (Box-folder 104A:24)
    - B.F. Price, Randolph Macon, Washington-Lee Society Rooms [Washington and Franklin Literary Societies]. (Box-folder 104A:25)
    - B.F. Price, St. Paul's in Haymarket [Va.], 1884. (Box-folder 104A:26)
    - William B. Price (Box-folder 104A:27)
  - Alexandria Buildings, 1859-1890 (Box-folder 104B:1-39)
    Files on individual buildings in Alexandria; the majority are associated with B.F. Price.
    - Richard Lloyd House (Box-folder 104B:1)
    - French house, 517 S. Washington: B.F. Price. (Box-folder 104B:2)
    - St. Paul's Lecture Room, 1859-1860 (Box-folder 104B:3)
    - Crump House, 381 S. Lee: B.F. Price, 1860 (Box-folder 104B:4)
    - Olivet Chapel: B.F. Price, 1860 (Box-folder 104B:5)
    - S.H. Janey and Son: B.F. Price, 1866 or 1879 (Box-folder 104B:6)
    - French Bookstore: B.F. Price, 1866? (Box-folder 104B:7)
    - St. Paul's [Restoration]: B.F. Price, 1867 (Box-folder 104B:8)
    - Market House: B.F. Price, 1869 (Box-folder 104B:9)
    - Columbus Street Houses: B.F. Price, 1870 (Box-folder 104B:10)
    - Market Steeple: B.F. Price, 1871-1873 (Box-folder 104B:11)
    - Corn Exchange: B.F. Price, 1871 (Box-folder 104B:12)
    - St. Paul's Rectory: B.F. Price, 1871 (Box-folder 104B:13)
    - Resheill [Risheill] and Hooge - near corner Cameron and Washington on Washington: B.F. Price, 1872 (Box-folder 104B:14)
    - W.H. Lambert House, 407 Duke: B.F. Price, 1872 (Box-folder 104B:15)
    - Christ Church Recotry, Marshall House: B.F. Price, 1873 (Box-folder 104B:16)
    - J.H.D. Smoot House: B.F. Price, 1873 (Box-folder 104B:17)
    - John Perry House: B.F. Price, 1873 (Box-folder 104B:18)
    - Thomas Perry House: B.F. Price, 1873 (Box-folder 104B:19)
    - Peabody School: B.F. Price, 1874 (Box-folder 104B:20)
    - Building on King: B.F. Price, 1874 (Box-folder 104B:21)
    - Henry Strauss Shop: B.F. Price, 1876 (Box-folder 104B:22)
    - Thomas Hoy Shop: B.F. Price, 1877 (Box-folder 104B:23)
    - McBurney's Grocery: B.F. Price, 1879 (Box-folder 104B:24)
    - R.C. Acton Shop: B.F. Price, 1879 (Box-folder 104B:25)
    - Lannon: B.F. Price, 1879 (Box-folder 104B:26)
    - St. John's Academy: B.F. Price, 1880 (Box-folder 104B:27)
    - Concordia Hotel: B.F. Price, 1880 (Box-folder 104B:28)
    - Julian Young [store]: B.F. Price, 1881 (Box-folder 104B:29)
    - Herbert Bryant House: B.F. Price, October 11, 1881 (Box-folder 104B:30)
    - Thomas Hoy House, 410 S. Fairfax: B.F. Price, 1882 (Box-folder 104B:31)
    - Trinity Methodist Episcopal Church: B.F. Price, 1883 (Box-folder 104B:32)
    - Thomas Hoy house on Washington near Cameron corner: B.F. Price, 1884 (Box-folder 104B:33)
    - Hydra[u]lion: B.F. Price, 1885 (Box-folder 104B:34)
    - Houses on Duke: B.F. Price, 1889 (Box-folder 104B:35)
    - Norton Memorial [Norton Hall, St. Paul's]: Palmer, 1897-1898 (Box-folder 104B:36)
    - Smoot Houses on King: B.F. Price, 1890 (Box-folder 104B:37)
    - [Virginia] Stewart [house]: B.F. Price, circa 1890 (Box-folder 104B:38)
    - Aspinwall (Box-folder 104B:39)
  - General Subjects (Box-folder 104B:40-48)
    - Christ Church and St. Mary's: B.F. Price (Box-folder 104B:40)
    - Carpenters Union (Box-folder 104B:41)
    - Painters, Artists (Box-folder 104B:42)
    - Introduction to builders (Box-folder 104B:43)
    - Builders (Box-folder 104B:44)
    - Black construction (Box-folder 104B:45)
    - Sources (general) (Box-folder 104B:46)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 104B:47)
    - Fire companies (Box-folder 104B:48)
- Historic Alexandria Foundation, 1984-1989 (Box 104C)
  - Antique Show advertisements, Antique Show invitation, stationery, membership brochure, correspondence. (Box-folder 104C:1)
  - The Plaque newsletter, 1984-1989. (Box-folder 104C:2)
  - Alexandria Academy. (Box-folder 104C:3)
  - The Alexandria Academy (was bound with source materials). (Box-folder 104C:4)
  - Education. (Box-folder 104C:5)
  - Buchanan, ... engineer's report, July/August 1987. (Box-folder 104C:6)